hello class today we will be talking
about error propagation now error and
uncertainty are pretty much synonymous
so we will be using them interchangeably
but before we talk about error
propagation let's go back and review
what error / uncertainty is if you
remember we took the example of the red
ribbon measurement in a few slides ago
actually in this case it's going to be a
few days ago I hope you remember that we
say that the we demonstrated that the
error is always on the last digit the
uncertainty story is on always on the
last digit because that digit is
estimated and we said all these numbers
to 65 to 60 62 67 or for that matter any
non-zero digit on the third or the
second decimal is valid so 64 65 66 67
68 all of those are good and that
includes also 61 and 69 so we could have
written the we could write the length of
the red ribbon as two point sixty six
plus or minus 0.01 centimeters this
could be symbolized as a which
represents two point sixty six plus or
minus Delta a and Delta a represents
0.01 centimeters and notice the units
they are very important in this case and
we will talk about that in a few seconds
now 0.01 centimeters is called or
centimeter is called absolute
uncertainty it has units always keep
that in mind now what would you call
0.01 over two point 66 yes you right we
would call that the relative uncertainty
and if you symbolize our Delta a over a
now the relative uncertainty could be
written many different ways it could be
written as a fraction such as in this
case which is 0.01 over two point 66 it
could also be written as a percentage
for example if
we had zero point if we had five over
100 that would be 0.05 or we could call
it five percent likewise if we had let's
say 20 over a thousand that would be two
percent okay so rotary uncertainty could
be written as a fraction as a percentage
it could even be written as a plus Delta
a now notice that there are no units in
this case that's the big difference
between our rotary uncertainty and
absolute uncertainty okay now root of
uncertainty is also a measurement of
precision we already mentioned that the
only difference between uncertainty and
error as far as we are concerned again
is that uncertainty is range and error
is a number remember for error we could
maybe we could calculate it by using
experimental value of minus accepted
value so that will give us one number so
that will be the error however
uncertainty as we have been seeing is
written as plus or minus a number dot a
so that would be a range okay so instead
of just being one number is going to be
arranged but as we are as far as we're
concerned again I'm repeating myself
here you know we can use those those two
those two words interchangeably so back
to error propagation there are two rules
that you need to know one of them is
about multiplication and division and
the second rule is about addition and
subtraction so rule one is about
addition and subtraction when two
numbers need to be added or subtracted
from each other then they are then the
the uncertainty of each must be
expressed in absolute form and then the
absolute uncertainty on the sum or the
difference he is going to be equal to
the sum of the absolute uncertainties of
the two numbers
let me repeat that if you have to
determine the absolute uncertainty of a
sum or a subtraction first you have to
express the the uncertainties of each
numbers in their absolute form and then
you add them up okay now you add them up
whether you're subtracting or adding
okay used at the yacht the uncertainties
are and this is important no it's just a
you know very simple algebra Delta a
equals Delta a over a times a so that
the A's cancel out so you're lucky the
Delta this is important because it will
help us determine the reabsorption
certainties when we have the relative
uncertainties just by multiplying by a
which is again the number rule number
two is about multiplication or division
so in this case if we need to determine
the vertical if you need to determine
the uncertainty first we have express
the uncertainties on the numbers in
their relative form and then we add the
two we add the two relative
uncertainties all right let's take
examples to clarify all this example one
let's say we have four centimeters plus
plus or minus 0.1 we need to add this to
12 centimeters plus or minus 0.2 so this
is an addition remember and this is an
addition and the uncertainty is here
what are they are they relative or are
they are they absolute they are relative
right because there are no units on them
so what we so now what we need to do is
convert them to absolute uncertainties
because for addition and subtraction
remember we have to express the numbers
in their absolute uncertainties and then
add them up so how do we get an absolute
uncertainty from a relative uncertainty
remember we have to multiply that by by
their number by a so we do that 0.10
which is the relative uncertainty on the
four centimeters we multiply that by 4
centimeters and we get zero point four
centimeters and then we do the same for
the uncertainty on the 12 centimeters so
that would
0.2 times the number itself which is 12
and we get to point for now we have the
absolute uncertainties so what we do is
we go ahead and add them up so 0.4 plus
2.4 left will be two point two point
eight centimeters okay now we add the
two numbers also obviously because we
are adding them so 4 plus 12 is 16 so
the final answer is going to be 16 plus
or minus 2.8 centimeters all right so
I'm still here so this is it we could
also go back if you want it to convert
it back to the relative uncertainties we
could go to point a which is now the
absolute uncertainty / 16 to get the
relative uncertainty and there you go
and notice that the units are not shown
here on zero point 18 all right so we
could also write it as percentage so
this is it for example 1 let's see the
example 2 now in this case we are
multiplying two numbers again
four-point-oh by 12 and we have an
absolute uncertainty of 0.1 0 on the
four and another episode uncertainty on
the 12 which is 0.20 first we have to
these uncertainties of course are
absolute because we have units on them
so we need to convert them to rotate
relative uncertainties and then we add
those electric uncertainties so you more
polite the phone numbers and then the
root of uncertainties are added so we go
ahead and figure out the irritable
certainties and then we go ahead and add
them so we'll multiply the two numbers
so 4 times 12 is 48 and we had the
favorite of uncertainties and here we go
oops here we go all right so this video
is already pretty much done nine minutes
long and I don't want the videos to be
to go beyond 10 minutes so feel free to
pause rewind
you know bleh anything you want and ask
questions in class tomorrow alright
thank you bye