PROFESSOR: In 1687, Sir
Isaac Newton invented
calculus, which became the
mathematical basis for physics.
In the context of physics and
science, functions typically
map numeric arguments
to numeric results,
but more advanced operations, like
differentiation and integration,
are functions that
manipulate other functions.
Instead of numbers, arguments
and results of functions
are themselves functions.
In 1941, Alonzo Church used this
trick of higher order functions
to invent the Lambda Calculus, which
via the church [? theory ?] thesis,
became the mathematical
basis for computer science.
Church was the world's
first functional hacker.
And showed how all of mathematics can
be modeled using just pure functions.
A few decades later
in 1960, John McCarthy
used the Lambda calculus to create
Lisp, one of the world's first
and finest computer
programming languages.
Lisp pioneered the idea of
to rethink functions as data.
The dual of Church's model
of data as functions.
Fast forward to 2014, and we see that
all modern programming languages such
as Haskell, PHP, C#, C++, JavaScript,
and even Java now support Lambda
expressions as first class citizens.
So for giants Facebook,
Twitter, Netflix, and Google,
are all powered by
functional programming.
Big data processing
techniques like MapReduce
come straight out of the
functional programmers PlayBook.
Amongst all languages
that support closures,
Haskell remains most faithful to
Church's original Lambda calculus,
and therefore, Haskell
is the ideal language
to teach you how to
program using functions.
As a serious practitioner
or student, you
don't have 300 years to make the
journey from Newton to Java 8,
but if you take this MOOC, we'll
get you up to speed in no time.
See you soon in cyberspace.