you
i ghen values and eigenvectors play a
critical role in determining observable
measurements of quantum systems in
evaluating the stability of mechanical
structures in analyzing the feedback
loops of electric circuits and in many
other areas to fully understand physics
and engineering it is necessary to
understand Augen values and eigenvectors
suppose we have an object
[Music]
here we are viewing the object from
different perspectives
[Music]
now suppose we apply what we call a
linear transformation
[Music]
as we again view the object from
different perspectives we see that the
object is now distorted let us consider
the points on this object before the
transformation
[Music]
each of these points can be represented
by an arrow
[Music]
when the transformation is applied the
length and direction of each arrow can
change
[Music]
there are some arrows that point along
the same line both before and after the
transformation for example these three
arrows will simply have their lengths
multiplied by a constant
the length of the orange arrow is
multiplied by negative 1 the length of
the blue arrow is multiplied by 2 and
the length of the green arrow is
multiplied by 1/2
[Music]
we say that negative 1/2 and 1/2 are the
eigenvalues of this transformation
the arrows that point along the same
line both before and after the
transformation are what we call the
eigenvectors
[Music]
the amounts by which the lengths of each
of these arrows is multiplied are what
we call the eigenvalues the eigenvalues
and eigenvectors dictate the nature of
the transformation for the entire object
consider for example the point
symbolized by this white arrow
the white arrow is not aligned with the
directions of any of the eigenvectors
which are symbolized by the orange green
and blue lines
[Music]
but the white arrow can be thought of as
a combination of arrows that are
parallel to the directions of these
three lines
[Music]
when the transformation is applied the
lengths of each of these arrows is
multiplied by the eigenvalue associated
with that direction
[Music]
that is the orange green and blue arrows
continue pointing in the same direction
but are multiplied by negative 1 1/2 and
2 in this way the transformation of any
point on this object can be determined
by using the eigenvalues and
eigenvectors the eigenvectors do not
necessarily have to be ninety degrees to
one another
for example let us consider this new
object and this new transformation
you
the red and green arrows are
eigenvectors of this transformation
you
the green arrow is multiplied by 1 and
the red arrow is multiplied by 2
you
now consider the transformation of this
white arrow
the white arrow can be thought of as the
combination of arrows parallel to the
green and red lines
during the transformation this green
arrow is multiplied by 1 and this red
arrow is multiplied by 2
[Music]
the eigenvalues and eigenvectors do not
necessarily have to consist of real
numbers
you
[Music]
the eigenvalues of this transformation
are the imaginary numbers I and negative
I and the eigenvectors are the following
you
let us say that the red arrow is
signified by a 1 followed by a 0
[Music]
and let's say that the yellow arrow is
signified by a zero followed by a one
[Music]
before the transformation the blue arrow
is in the same direction as the red
arrow but double its length
[Music]
therefore using the notation described
the blue arrow before the transformation
would be signified by a 2 followed by a
[Music]
after the transformation the blue arrow
is pointed in the opposite direction of
the yellow arrow and double its length
therefore the blue arrow after the
transformation would be signified by a
zero followed by a negative - let's
consider the blue arrow before the
transformation
[Music]
the blue arrow can be thought of as the
sum of the two eigenvectors
[Music]
suppose we multiply each eigenvector by
its corresponding eigenvalue
[Music]
the result is the new direction of our
blue arrow after the transformation
[Music]
therefore everything discussed here is
still true even for imaginary values for
eigenvalues and eigenvectors much more
information about linear transformations
is available in the video linear algebra
matrix transformations please subscribe
for notifications when new videos are
ready