in this session we are going to
introduce spectral clustering method why
do we want to do spectral clustering
because spectral clustering have some
unique advantages so first
spectral clustering makes no assumption
on the shapes of clusters so you can
cluster like any kind of a shape even
intertwine spiders you'll be able to
find nice and neat clusters not to say
other shapes however many other
classroom like a k-means or e/m tend to
find non convex shaped clusters then
another advantage is usually e/m or like
a k-means those are will require an
iterative process to find local minimum
and they are very sensitive to
initialization so you usually need
multiple restarts to get a high quality
clusters
however spectral clustering where you
have no such burden okay the general
process of spectral clustering is
partitioning into these three steps the
first step is construct a similarity
graph for example we can use ten years
Nabal pays down their neighborhood using
like a Euclidean distance or other
distances you like to do your clustering
okay then for all the points you can
construct such similarity graph for
example if you look at this illustrative
example you can see the original data
points if you choose symmetric K nearest
neighbor you will find the skinners
negative neighbor graph like the
following then we can embed the data
points in a low dimensional space using
spectral class embedding what is this
this essentially is we can do graph
laplacian compute the eigenvectors of
such graph laplacian
sir this embedding the cluster
structures become more obvious then we
will be able to apply classical
clustering algorithm like a gay means on
these embedding that means we will be
able to partition the embedding graph
into nice clusters so this is the
general idea now we look at how we do it
step by step first suppose we have a
graph this usually is obtained by the K
nearest neighbor then we get awaits
suppose the way to W sub 1 2 is a weight
connecting the vertices 1 and a 2 ok
then the adjacency matrix is M by M
symmetric matrix like this one then for
each element what you got the the
assignment is if there's an edge between
like a 1 and 2 then you can pass on the
edge weight W sub 1 2 you can get that
weight W sub IJ is the weight of this
sale
if there is no connected edge like 1 4
is not connected then 1 for this cell
will be assigned as 0 then we can
perform laplacian on these matrix
essentially is we use a diagonal matrix
of degrees
- this adjacency matrix will get a
laplacian what is the eigen or matrix of
the degrees simply says you the degree
is defined by for each row you just sum
up all the degree all the weights or you
say all the cell values in in this row
for example for Row 1 what you get is W
sub 1 2 plus W sub 1 3 you get the
weights that's the degree you will get
that's d1 similarly for other degrees
you just
in the same way laplacian this matrix
value is if this one is diagonal matrix
I equals J then you get the D sub I okay
that's the row value of this degree if
the if its other cells like I J has an
edge then because 0 minus this w sub IJ
you get minus W sub IJ that's what you
got
if original was 0 you will still get 0
okay so that's the value you get from
calculus laplacian matrix then we can
see how we can calculate the graphs for
eigenvalue and eigenvector so we pro can
see the eigen value computation is based
on this formula which has been used very
popularly in linear algebra in matrix
computation we're not getting to very
detail but general philosophy is you get
a matrix a lambda is an eigenvalue of a
and for some vector V you will follow
this this equation and V is icon vector
and the lambda is the eigen value of a
ok so then for a graph G if we have n
nodes then its adjacency you will have n
eigen values and this n value you can
sort them according to the descending
order you get lambda 1 lambda 2 to
lambda sub n of this n corresponding
eigen vectors will be X sub 1 to X sub n
you look at this figure why you can see
this is the original graph you we have 6
vertices and their connections where the
connection is marked using those way
those values ok then obviously the the
original matrix adjacency matrix is
marked here you pro can see and that's
the original
easy matrix then we can calculate the
this originally a I this matrix
eigenvalue and you pro can see this is
their eigenvalues and you pray you see
this is mu 1 to MU 6 okay so that's the
spec spectrum of the graph then the
eigenvalue and eigenvector of the graph
the graph laplacian of G is Keira kated
you for this graph essentially is you
get a lambda 1 lambda 2 2 lambda n and
we know the value of lambda 1 lambda 2
lambda n we can sort them in this order
okay so if this 0 0 you get a spectrum
is you you get this lambda value that's
eigenvalue and eigenvector then
eigenvalue review is a global graph
property which is not apparent from the
edge structure itself essentially if you
get a 0 is the eigenvalue with k
different eigen vectors you probably
will see these essentially the k k come
connected components that means if
lambda y is 0 that rapin the one
connected component then if graph is
connected then lambda 2 will be greater
than 0 lambda 2 is energy bright
connectivity of g here you can see the
energy air sub G has lambda 1 lambda 2
lambda 3 as 0 you get a 3 connected
components and if you have air this g1
g2 you can see G 1 is has only one
connected component and G
who also has one connected component
that's why lambda 2 is greater than zero
however you also can see g2 is much
denser is much more connected than g1
that's why G 2 lambda 2 value will be
greater than G ones lambda 2 value then
we can work out the partitioning via
spectral measures the general philosophy
is if we get this original graph we map
them into la blushing of this original
graph is this value okay then we
actually also know we can carry it the
second the second eigenvector and the
second back again vector V sub two
corresponding to lambda sub 2 and for
lambdas up to the smaller the better
quality of the partitioning because if
lambda is 0 means it's not connected and
if lambda 2 actually greater means they
they are more tightly connected if you
want to get nice partitioning you want
to find a smaller lambda 2 then if we
calculated this for each node I and G we
can assign it the value of V 2 then we V
2 sub I so for for example these note
once V 2 is zero point one at zero point
four one then if we want to find these
are the six nodes they are corresponding
V 2 value then if we get this V 2 value
we can get a greater than 0 then we can
assign to C 1 and these vetoes the value
is less than 0 it could be another
cluster then we actually will get a nice
partitioning C 1 C 2
this 1 2 3 will become one cluster 4 5 6
will become another cluster so we can
extend this algorithm to K partitions
the gain in Jordan and in the vise
algorithm you know work out it by
engineering Michael Jordan and and this
publishing 2002 was normalized laplacian
essentially the original a poverty is
not a normalized but once you use this
formula we can ominous a graph so the
degree the part is all one and all the
other roles you add up actually is -1 so
you finally get it normalized graph so
we can compute the first K eigen vectors
we want to be K then we can carat the
the matrix that you use in a similar way
we can do the partition into you know
because we take the ice role of you it's
a feature factor after normalizing to
normal one no one can cluster the points
which k-means into K clusters then this
Messer is commonly used as a dimension
reduction dimensionality reduction
measures for clustering