machines can't read obviously but then
ever wonder how Google knows exactly
what you're looking for just as you
write it imagine one day I gave you an
article and asked you what is this
article about you would probably read it
quickly and be able to tell me this
article is about Mars the planet but I
tell you to wait your job is not yet
done I now hand you a whole pile of
articles and ask you what each of them
is about this would probably infuriate
you because the only way you could do
that is to read through all of them but
what if I told you you don't have to
let's take the Mars article for example
if I took out a couple of words from the
article could you still tell me what it
was about it wouldn't make any sense now
but you know it had something to do with
Mars the planet machines read the same
way discounting words but you should
stop me right here you know what mark
says you've heard about it before how
does a machine know what it is well by
something called inference for instance
if I told you that a box contained some
red and white colored balls and we pick
out 10 balls from it some red and some
white then what is the ratio of the
balls in the box you could count out of
10 we have five red balls and five white
balls so with some confidence you could
say the ratio should be half of them red
and half of them white machines do the
same thing for articles they would count
the word Mars then they would count the
other words that showed up in the
article they would do that for all the
articles in the pile and then with some
confidence say Mars is probably a planet
and you thought reading was easy